Charles James Rhoads Papers 1883-1929 Mss.B.R34
American Philosophical Society
Charles James Rhoads Papers
1883-1929
Mss.B.R34
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Linear feet
Letters and telegrams, mostly of congratulation, relating to Charles James Rhoads's appointment as United States Commissioner of Indian Affairs by President Hoover in 1929; with drafts of some replies. Correspondents include Emily G. Balch, Felix Frankfurter, and Herbert C. Hoover. The collection also includes several letters from James E. Rhoads to Capt. Richard H. Pratt of the Indian Training School, Carlisle, 1883-1894, and copies of a few letters from Pratt to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, 1913-1921, on Indian matters.
Rhoads, Charles James,1872-1956.
Related Archival Materials note
The Records of the Indian Rights Association are housed at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania (Collection 1523).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Rhoads Papers came to the American Philosophical Society Library in 1965 as a gift of Brown Brothers, Harriman and Company (Philadelphia, Pa.), through Mrs. Thatcher Brown III.
Scope and Contents note
The Rhoads Papers consists of two distinctly different parts, the first pertaining to the appointment of Charles James Rhoads as Commissioner of Indian Affairs in 1929, and the second relating to his and his father's interests in Indians. Among the latter are several personal letters from R. H. Pratt, Superintendent of the Indian Training School at Carlisle Barracks, Pa., to James Rhoads; printed material related to Indian affairs and problems; handwritten notes and typed essays regarding Indian affairs.
Series I. Correspondence 1929 0.75 linear feet
Series II. James E. Rhoads Papers 1883-1921 0.25 linear feet
Series III. Miscellaneous notes on Indian affairs n.d. 1 folder
Biographical/Historical note
Charles James Rhoads was born in Germantown, Philadelphia on October 4, 1872. After attending William Penn Charter School and Haverford College, receiving his bachelors degree in 1893, Rhoads was worked in various positions with the Banking Department of the Girard Trust Company. He rose quickly in the company, becoming Treasurer at the age of twenty-eight and Vice-President four years later. He married Lillie Frishmuth in 1912.
In 1914, Rhoads was selected to become the first governor of the Federal Reserve Bank in Philadelphia, but still remained a member of the Board of Managers at Girard Trust. After the United States entered World War I in 1917, Rhoads, a member of the Society of Friends, contributed to the war effort as a civilian volunteer. He resigned from the Federal Reserve Bank and served the Y.M.C.A. by raising funds for its work, later traveling overseas as Chair of its program, Prisoners of War Relief.
Following the Armistice, Rhoads took charge of Quaker relief and construction projects in France. Subsequently, he returned to America and became President of the Central National Bank. In 1929, President Herbert Hoover requested Rhoads to serve as a Commissioner of Indian Affairs. He had knowledge of Indian problems because of the interests of his father, James E. Rhoads who helped establish the Indian Rights Association. His lifelong friend J.Henry Scattergood, who assisted him in France, accompanied Charles Rhoads to Washington as Assistant Commissioner of Indian Affairs. Their policies emphasized the home and community as the center of Indian life and education. Rhoads again took an active role in Indian affairs in 1948 as a member of the Hoover Commission.
Charles Rhoads was a devoted member of the Society of Friends, and very active within the Philadelphia area business and academic communities. For thirty-six years he served as a member of the Boards of the Provident Mutual Life Insurance and the Philadelphia Savings Fund Society. His association with Bryn Mawr College began in 1907 when he was elected a Member of the Trustees and later in 1936 became President of the Trustees and Chairman of the Board of Directors. He held both offices until his death in 1956 whereon the College was the beneficiary of his "residuary" estate.
Balch, Emily Greene, 1867-1961; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Pratt, Richard Henry, 1840-1924; Rhoads, James E., (James Evans), 1828-1895; United States. Commissioner of Indian Affairs; Indians of North America; Telegrams
- Series I. Correspondence, 1929; 0.75 lin. feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Where there are multiple letters by the same correspondent, those letters are arranged chronologically. The date or date span of the correspondence is noted after the name of the correspondent. Additionally, in Series I there is a folder titled: Unidentified correspondence and illegible signatures.
  - Abeel, Neilson, April 19, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Mr. & Mrs. J.P., April 19, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Ashbridge, Mary, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Bachman, Ida, April 25/? (Box 1)
  - Balch, Emily, May 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Bennett, Katerine, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Biddle, Edith, May 27, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Biddle, Francis, April 22, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Biddle, William, April 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Billikoff, J., April 18, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, William, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Thatcher, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Brownlee, Fred, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Bullard, Ethel, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Burleson, Hugh, May 20, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Cadbury, Henry, May l, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Canby, William, June 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Chapman, Ellword, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Chorley, Kenneth, April 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Cloud, H.R., April 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Coffin, W.V., April 23, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Collier, John, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Collins, A.M., April 26, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Comfort, W.W., April 19-5/l, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, C.W., April 30, 1929 (Box 1)
  - County, A.J., April 18-5/11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Crumbine, S.J., April 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Curtis, Bridgeham, April 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Curtis, Louis Jr., May 20, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Dale, E.E., April 22, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Carroll, April 13, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Dawson, Emily F., April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Dennis, William, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Duane, Richard, April 28, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Eliot, Samuel, April 13, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Elliot, C.L., April 29, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Evans, Chas., May 19, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Evans, Edward, April 22, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Evans, Harold, April 19, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Delano, Moreau, April 15, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Dodson, Alan, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Farnam, Henry, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Fawcett, James, June 7, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Galen, April 26, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Fox, Logan, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Frankfurter, Felix, June 6, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Friedberg, Ralph, May 18, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Garrett, Helen, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Goodhart, Howard, May 2, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Grant, Elihu, April 26, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Gregg, James, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Griffin, Frederick, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Grinnell, G., April 26, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Fry, Ruth, February 22, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Gummere, Richard, April 20, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hagerman, Herbert, April 29, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hawkins, Nana, June 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hendrick, Ellwood, April 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hendy, Dora, April 20, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hertz, Randolph, June 10, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hilles, S., May 4, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hood, E.G., May 10, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hoover, Herbert, April 9, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Howland, Chas., April 18, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hudson, M. O., April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hughes, William, May 9, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hutchinson, M., April 23, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Ingersoll, E., n.d. (Box 1)
  - Kane, Francis, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Keen, W.W., April 12-4/17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Kenworthy, Murray, May 9-5/21, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Kimber, Natalie, April 19, 1929 (Box 1)
  - King, Clyde, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Kirkbride, Franklin, April 20, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Jackson, Lucy, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Jackson, Percy, April 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Jastrow, Helen, April 15, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Jenkins, Chas., April 18, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, H.A., April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Jones, T.J., April 11-4/19, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Laughlin, S.B., April 20, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Lathrop, Julia C., April 24-4/30, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Leach, A.B., May 7, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Libby, Fred, May 14, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Lindquist, G. E., April 29, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Lippmann, W., May 3, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Livingood, Chas., April 16, 1929 (Box 1)
  - McCouch, Gordon, April 18/? (Box 1)
  - McDonald, James, April 22, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Mack, Elmer, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - McKittrick, M., June 11, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Magill, James, April 30, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Maier, Paul, April 23, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Marvel, J., April 23, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Martin, Elizabeth, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Maule, Margaret, April 17, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Mengert, Ulric, April 19, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Meriam, Lewis, April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Moor, G.C., April 12, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Morris, Lawrence, May 27, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Morris, S.W., April 19, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Moulton, H.G., April 11-4/25, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Mustard, W.P., April 13, 1929 (Box 1)
  - N.Y.C. Indian Assn., April 15, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Norris, George W., April 18, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Norton, Marion, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Patterson, Ernest, May 13, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Pease, Henry, April 20, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Peabody, G., April 17, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Pennington, Levi, May 21, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Pfaelzer, E.L., April 17, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Pickett, Clarence, May 23, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Pinchot, Gifford, May 8, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Rhoads, Alex, May l, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Rhoads, Chas. J., April 14-4/17, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Rhoads, George, May l, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Rice, William, May 21, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Richie, H., April 22, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Robertson, J., April 20, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Robins, Margaret, April 15, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Rome, ?, April 13-7, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Rushmore, S., May 16, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Sells, Cato, April 11-12, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Siddons, Fred, April 11, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Slade, Louis, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Smeltzer, Robert, April 20, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Josp., May 26-June 10, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Sparhawk, Frances, May 4, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Starlight, A., April 11, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Stuie, John, April 21/? (Box 2)
  - Sweetser, Arthur, April 17, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Taylor, Burgess, April 30, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Thomas, E.B., May 23, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Thomas, Wilbur, May 1, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Tippy, Worth, April 11, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Toplitz, S., April 13, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Trueblood, W.O., April 28, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Tunney, Josp., April 24, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Tuttle, Florence, April 24, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Van Loon, E.P., April 11, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Van Schaick, John, April 22, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Vickery, H.F., April 12, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Villard, O.G., April 26, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Vincent, G.E., April 12, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Walcott, Mary, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Wald, Lillian, May 14, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wallerstein, D., April 17, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Walton, G., May 15, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Welsh, Herb., April 16, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Weston, S., April 20, 1929 (Box 2)
  - White, A.E., April 11-27, 1929 (Box 2)
  - White, Daniel, April 11, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wichersham, George, April 22, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wilbur, Lyman Ray, March 26-April 15, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wilbur,B.K., April 30, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Williams, Chas., April 23, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Willits, Josp., May 6, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wilson, Alan, April 22, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wistar, E.M., April 17, 1929 (Box 2)
  - W.B.D.M. Church, April 12, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wood, Carolena, April 11, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wood, L.H., April 18/? (Box 2)
  - Wood, John, April 13, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wood, Richard, April 29, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Woods, S.S., April 17, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Woodruff, Clinton, April 11, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Woolman, Edward, May 19, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wright, Burnet, May 29, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Wright, Minturn, April 11, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified correspondence and illegible signatures. (Box 2)
- Series II. James E. Rhoads Papers, 1883-1921; 0.25 lin. feet
  The correspondence from James E. Rhoads to R.H. Pratt, head of the Indian Training School at Carlisle Barracks, Pa., are arranged chronologically; the remainder of the correspondents are arranged alphabetically.
  - Burke, Chas. H., June 13, 1921 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., May 5 1883 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., May 22, 1883 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., June 18, 1886 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., June 23, 1886 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., December 7, 1886 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., December 6, 1889 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., December 5, 1890 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., December 12, 1891 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., February 10, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., May 26, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, R.H., July ? 1894 (Box 2)
  - Sells, Cato, July 12, 1914 (Box 2)
- Series III. Correspondence, 1 folder
  Various handwritten notes, and four typed essays on Indian affairs arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Notes and essays related to Indian affairs (Box 2)
    Includes essays by: S.M. Brosius, Dr. Haven Emerson, Charles F. Jenkins, M.K. Sniffen